[Music]
[Applause]
welcome to the high existence podcast
where we challenge the way you live we
bring you the wisdom and tools to help
you grow into a more enlightened version
of yourself join us by taking the
ultimate life experiment my thirty
challenges to enlightenment course a
complete spiritual path to help you
overcome the limitations of your mind
and to embody the highest philosophical
realizations use the code wisdom a check
out to get a huge twenty five percent
off the course available only to podcast
subscribers at store a existence calm
I'm your host John mortal oh you can
find me over on high existence and on my
own podcast voices in the dark hey
welcome to the high existance podcast
I'm John Waterlow joined by Martin sharp
well we welcome we have a great guest
this week Daniel SH macton Berger who is
a found at the neuro hacker collective a
movement dedicated to upgrading our
individual and collective capacities and
to safeguarding the well-being of all
he's an evolutionary philosopher systems
designer a strategist and I could
probably keep throwing lots of labels
around and that's still kind of apply
there's a lot of crossover between
different fields which i think is
something that we're going to explore in
this episode so Daniel thank you very
much for joining us thank you for having
me fun to be here how do you how do you
feel about the labels in fact when
trying to sum up the things that you're
interested in I like talking about
things that I'm interested in more than
labels of things that I am or I'm not so
when in general when people are wanting
to ask what my background is whatever
out I like sharing things that I'm
passionate about and I like asking
people similarly what they're interested
in and yeah as you said there's a lot of
overlapping interests when you have a
deep fascination with the nature of
reality and everything within it
yeah I think it's good to start with the
the things that you're interested in
rather than making identity statements
so what what do you think how would you
sum up the the mission of neuro hacker
collective and what what drives and
prompted you to do the things that you
do and what the collective is aiming to
do mm-hmm so the collective is an
awesome project and it's one project
that I've associated with and there are
other projects I'm associate would they
do very different things so what its
mission is and what moves me are
partially overlapping the goal of neural
hacker is really at an individual level
increasing human well-being and human
capacity and right in that right now
it's mostly focused on the physiology
side of that but is eventually
interested in the psychology and
psychological cognitive development side
as well but specifically looking at the
how physiology effects psyche both
states of experience emotion you know
well-being and capacities and working to
do a better job of how we support
physiologies to predispose happier and
more capable and more positively
oriented people is really the interest
of it and in terms of what we're doing
so far that's exploring the space of
what you could think of as kind of
psycho neuropharmacology or psychiatry
but rather than just looking at single
molecule solutions how do we address
dopamine through one synthetic molecule
or address serotonin or one synthetic
molecule trying to look at is is there
anything even imbalance with this
person's dopaminergic system do we know
and if so where did the imbalance occur
and do we understand about the
regulatory systems that are involved and
what would a more comprehensive approach
to supporting those regulatory systems
to do better and is dopamine the only
thing that was imbalanced if it was
where
their other neurotransmitters involved
were their other nutrient amounts as
involved where their gut brain access or
neuro inflammatory dynamics so how do we
do a better job of understanding the
physiology as a whole as a subset of
then not just physiology but the mind
brain environment complex but starting
even just with physiology how do we
understand how the different systems
interact with each other more complexly
how do they self-regulate what leads to
increased homeostatic resilience or
decreased homeostatic resilience or
deviation from homeostasis
and how can we do a better job of both
understanding these systems and
supporting these systems to have more
resilience and more capacity so that's
the goal of neural hacker and if you
know if anyone goes to the website and
checks it out with what they'll see
right now is some information about that
mission writ large but then they'll see
one offering which is you know we we we
had a first offering that was kind of
how do we do something better than the
smart drugs that people are taking to
increase productive capacity but that
increase a fairly narrow bandwidth of
productive capacity oftentimes at the
expense of other meaningful aspects so
maybe we get more focused but certain
memory metrics decrease certain
creativity metrics decrease and maybe
things like empathy decrease anxiety can
increase and it's doing it in a way that
creates long term dependence and
down-regulation can we increase a
broader set of the things that are
meaningful for people and do it in a way
where because it's working through and
with their endogenous regulatory systems
rather than overriding them if they're
on something like this for a while and
then get off of it they don't have
dependence and crash and if anything
they have lasting elevation of baseline
those were our goals and you know we're
working on that for a number of other
categories not just in the productivity
category but that that was the first
thing that we were able to get far
enough with to have as an offer
- that's neural hacker yes and that's
that those are the kind of the areas
where we're going to get into in a later
episode with the personal development
but I think if we look at the the bigger
picture of societies and where we are
across the world it's almost the same
problem but talking at the collective
level about how we can optimize what we
have and try and raise and change some
baselines away from if there are
depleted or dangerous levels do you see
them as sort of overlapping goals in in
that respect the the collective
optimization or is it a different sort
of perspective the human brain the human
physiology the human psyche and culture
and ecology are all complex systems
right self-organizing complex systems
and we are not that good at interacting
with and supporting complex systems yet
we the whole field of complexity science
is still a brand new field and hasn't
really entered that meaningfully into
how we approach things like design we're
quite good at simple systems and we're
also pretty good at complicated systems
so when I look at something like the LAT
laptop I'm talking to you on the
blueprint for how to make it from you
know the transistor level all the way up
to all the parts hitting together
software I mean there's a tremendous
amount of information no one person
could do it it takes a tremendous number
of people but there is a blueprint and
it doesn't evolve itself in real time
right so it's a static design it was
designed the computer didn't design
itself it's designed from outside of
itself it doesn't repair itself as
opposed to when we look at biology and
we see systems that organize and emerge
in relationship with their environments
but without exogenous design and where
they don't have a formal blueprint the
blueprint itself is changing the
structure of it is changing in every
interaction
even if we look at the genome the
genetic expression is changing and you
know etc so what what happens is when
we're dealing with a complex system like
human physiology and we if there's an
acute cause of an issue like an injury
we're pretty good at that in medicine
dealing with things like injuries it
doesn't mean we won't get a lot better
an exponential tech will help us get a
lot better but when we're dealing with
something like cancer or autoimmune
disease or neurodegenerative disease or
something that doesn't have an obvious
acute cause it has complex causation and
that might mean that there isn't one
cause there's a number of different
causes and they might not be the same
for different people so you might be
looking autoimmune disease where
infection was part some kind of
subclinical infection was part of a
destabilization of homeo dynamic systems
and some kind of toxicity exposure and
maybe some kind of nutrient deficiency
combined with some kind of genetic
predisposition right all came together
to lead to a series of imbalances that
eventually we call MS or rheumatoid
arthritis or whatever it is and so not
only might it be multifactorial right
but it might have many steps of causal
transform the infection leading to
changed immune cells leading to
autoimmune antibodies you know etc and
that happened over the course of time
and you have this delayed time causation
all of this makes it much harder to
assess cause and effect and so you need
really a deeper system that isn't just
working with one variable at a time and
where there's clear causation but they
can do this kind of complex causal
assessment in the same way that we are
just starting with functional medicine
and systems biology to try and
understand the human physiology more
complexly
but we have dealt with it pretty much
like oh you have a tumor let's cut it
out rather than understand
carcinogenesis well cut it out or
radiate it out or poison it out and they
we've really dealt with global issues
we've dealt with the environment in very
much the same way the temperature is too
high so let's do geoengineering to
address decreasing temperature but
that's not addressing the cause of why
the temperatures too high at all because
we really don't know how to do that well
enough there's too many complex economic
and social and worldview and
technological factors so we largely deal
with it symptomatically well there with
Ward's symptomatically without
understanding all of the things that
lead to patterns of human experience and
behavior that lead to war and so I would
say that one of the things I'm really
interested in is understanding that
universe is a complex not a complicated
system that just like our computer our
civilization most of what we have built
as civilization has been complicated
systems complex systems are anti fragile
inherently like in a in a forest each
tree is exactly the way that it is in
relationship with everything else around
and it's changing and adapting in real
time it's contextual right and because
of all the ratio of aerobic to anaerobic
microbes of certain kinds of plants with
others ones that fix nitrogen and take
nitrogen you can't get one bug that's
gonna devastate everything there's gonna
be predators for that bug there's not
gonna be that much it likes whereas you
contrast that to row crops and you can
get a bug that can devastate everything
right the row cropping is fragile it is
susceptible to collapse in a way that
you know robust complex biospheres
aren't and we can think of physiologies
you know in a similar way we can think
of culture in a similar way well what we
have called civilization so far has been
a process of converting complex systems
into simple and complicated ones and
that doesn't mean it hasn't done
anything good but it has been kind of a
entropy generator in that way when you
think of evolution as increasing
elegantly ordered complexity that has
more synergy leading to new emergent
properties we take a tree than a
forest that has an indefinite number of
value metrics right like its value to
pollinators and its value to stabilizing
the topsoil in to sequestering co2 and
producing oxygen and home for these
kinds of animals and just all these
things and and the fish a thousand miles
away that have different water because
of the way it stabilizes topsoil and the
people that eat the fish generations
down down who are going to have
different epigenetic patterns because of
it like the tree is in this radically
interconnected complex system so you say
how do how do you even assess its value
its totally non-functional non and are
exchangeable with any like it and you
can't even quantify it but if I kill it
and turn it into two by fours that two
by four is not really adapting or
changing it slowly degrades but
otherwise it's a fixed thing I extract
it from its environment it has all I
care about it's a tensional and
compressional strength two things and I
really am going to take that even
further and just measure it in dollars
and make it accumulate able or
exchangeable when we look at that
process I took something that was
contextualized and complex I D
contextualized it brought it into a
lower degree of coming of complexity and
in the process we're making we're
actually making human civilization our
whole habitability here fragile and so
I'm very interested in how we can
understand universe and nature and
reality better how we can understand
complexity and self-organization better
so that we can work with the systems
that like economics is just made up
monopoly right like what our governments
are made up systems but ecology isn't
and biology isn't and psychology there
are intrinsic stew it even though
there's plenty of made up stuff in there
so how do we understand those better so
that we can work with them in ways that
support real thriving of the things that
are fundamentally meaningful in trying
to understand that and thinking thinking
how much expertise needs to go into it
is but I was thinking back to what you
first said about
the nature of the body that when it say
we have a disease or a disorder of some
kind there can be so many interlaced
interlocking causal factors yet doctors
are often experts in just one of those
so is there potentially an expert
problem here that lots of people are in
their particular fields say economics
and they only see things through the
economics lens do we need to have more
Jack's of all trades involved or is this
a case of I don't know RiRi
understanding what you need to be to be
an expert yeah so an expert in a
complicated system see one of the things
about a complicated system is you can
break it apart into parts and understand
the parts in isolation and put it back
together and you don't have the same
kinds of synergies that you have in
complex self-organizing systems so no
one has to understand every part of the
computer because we can take it apart
and put a new CPU in put a new hard
drive in and you notice that we've
treated bodies very much like that like
oh this parts worn out let's take it out
put a new one in or you don't really
need this part as opposed to like whoa
what happened with the regulatory
systems here and what role did it really
play and and you a gastroenterologist
can't you know in a neurologist and
oncologist they can't really understand
any of those parts independent of the
other ones because what's happening in
the gut via the microbiome via the gut
brain access via the enteric nervous
system via so many different kinds of
pathways is affecting what's happening
in the nervous system and then all of
the top-down mechanisms so there's I
wouldn't I wouldn't say that an expert
problem is how I would describe it I
would say there's a problem of hyper
specialization in complex systems where
that is just not the right epistemology
and Alfred North Whitehead wrote this
great paper some decades ago called the
problem of over specialization he said
notice how we the smarter a kid is the
earlier we start moving them into
specialization and we move them further
and further into specialization so that
by the time they do their PhD there's a
few people in the world that really
understand their dissertation and they
have relatively little abstraction
across domains lateral thinking into
other spaces etc because they're
supposed to be able to do a good job of
that specialized expertise and of course
we know there were benefits of
specialization but I think then there
were real problems with it you said so
when all of our a students are thinking
about tiny tiny parts then who's
thinking about the hole and so we are
leaving two people who didn't you know
excel that well to think about it or
just nobody at all and it is just a
complex kind of system but it's not
necessarily the one that we want or that
works effectively so I wouldn't say what
we want is jack-of-all-trades that's
kind of a false dichotomy I would say
people who are studying complex systems
and who are studying systems at all and
who are studying deeper level
generalized principles and things like
design that are cross applicable so that
they can so that they really have the
right epistemology to understand the
systems that they're looking at and to
work with them yes I think that's
critical and I think it's been critical
for a while but especially in the face
of machine learning within narrow
intelligence right now already and over
the next little bit narrow intelligence
via machine learning will just be better
at us better than us at combinatorics
with in finite spaces and it really is
generalized intelligence that is at the
meaningful place for humans to develop
themselves and work yeah and in that
case it's um it looks like the education
system and the way that we value certain
kinds of education is going to need to
change and I've heard you speak
passionately and passionately in the
past about an issue that we damp down
kids curiosity in the traditional
education systems and say no stop
looking at that stop playing with that
you need to go and learn these specific
exercises so I wonder how you think we
can reawaken that kind of curiosity
without fear and when I say fear I mean
the fear of parents or older generations
because they might want to nurture it in
their kids they might want
understand the necessity for it but if
they don't have any answers themselves
cuz they've only the parents have only
got this old-fashioned education how can
we overcome this this divide and find a
way to nurture it in children the other
thing that we call modern Western
education is not the only system of
Education that has ever been explored
and it's I don't think it's very hard to
have the educational philosophy argument
that it is just not even a very good one
for many definitions of what is a
meaningful way to educate a human being
but when you look at kind of the history
of how it came about and things like we
need you know the movement into an
industrial revolution where we needed
people we needed a lot of people to get
trained to fulfill roles within the
industrial revolution that we're pretty
fungible right factory line workers were
pretty fun like any of them could do
basically what any of the other ones
could do and MBAs are supposed to be
able to do pretty much what the other
ones can do and doctors and so how do we
the society needs people to fulfill
these roles so how do we create both an
extrinsic incentive economics to get
them to do it and how do we create an
education system to train them up into
these roles were then we identify them
with this role and this role is really
fun jables anyone else who had that
training give or take a little bit
there's gonna be profound
meaninglessness and that because the
uniqueness of self is gone their own
kind of self-directed process is gone
right and again especially in the place
of robotic automation where those jobs
are going to be getting automated and
not just physical robotic automation but
even the deep deep learning through a
lot of the things that we think of as
thinking things but things that are
procedural aiza bulimics possible and
necessitates a foundational rethinking
of what education should be for and
really like what society what
civilization should be for and it is
rather if we if we can decouple to where
the jobs don't need the people
to do them we can also decoupler to
where the people don't need the jobs
meaning start to actually change the
economic structure because we don't need
it to be a source of extrinsic incentive
then we get to say okay now we can
actually have a system of entry where
intrinsic incentive is deeper to both
the economics and the education so what
is an education system where the focus
is facilitating each child's unique
expression their unique passion interest
curiosities capacities and following it
right now you say how can parents how
can teachers participate with that if
they weren't facilitated that way and
they don't necessarily know the answer
and the kit the kids gonna ask them
questions they don't know answers to if
the parents earn this if they really are
earnest about this they can go on a
process of code discovery with their kid
and when the kid says so why is the sky
blue and the parent realizes that they
don't actually know they remember
something about diffraction but maybe it
is reflecting the ocean they don't
really fuck him outright then they can
be like well let's pour it together yes
and then rather than push for that
exploration to go in the way that
they're interested in pay attention to
the kids interest and ask them like war
find out why they're interested in it
and what there's what their intuition
about it is what their thought is and
help help go through the process of
helping them learn how to learn and
facilitating their interest in life and
letting their interest in life and their
learning reignite the adults also I
think that's that's a key ingredient
that you mentioned I hadn't sort of
which is not only to go and find the
answer for the kid but say first of all
what what do you think and why do you
wonder that and try and tune into into
the nature of that curiosity it's the
the dynamic that I often see and I even
feel it myself is a sort of sense a
little bit of shame and fear if someone
asked me a question I feel I ought to
know the answer to
and so it's a kind of a conversation to
about putting aside our own ego and need
to appear there sitting way in front of
others well there's a there's a few fun
things here so let's first address the
part about asking the kid why they're
interested so the kid asks why the sky
is blue maybe that was the question I
asked in the moment but they're just
really curious about why any color has
color and they could just as easily ask
why is the leaf green and they really
just want to know what color is right
and or they're really asking kind of a
question about God an existential thing
is about like why did the Creator make
it that way because that's the way
they're thinking about it and so they
they're there's a they're thinking about
things like why is anything the way that
it is or they're asking a question about
why is it that we subjectively
experience it as blue and does that
relate to what is objectively true and
do we all experience it the same way if
you don't know you're gonna go in to
answering it the way you think they're
asking it and then you're gonna find
them get bored pretty quickly and then
you're gonna get frustrated and try and
get them to pay attention and so it's
pretty important to actually pay
attention to what is the real inquiry
and then not you go find the answer as
if the answer already fucking exists
they might be asking questions the
answers don't fully exist - and you get
to like be in that process of discovery
together
where the answer matters less then the
investigation the inquiry the thinking
about it and some of the best questions
or when they get to things where we
don't know the answers and their
intuition about it might be as good as
anybody's yeah that's that the whole I
guess the the stereotype the picture of
the from the mouths of babes thing where
you start seeing the world from a new
angle just because somebody is asking a
question which is unencumbered by years
of cultural conditioning yeah and you
know if we're asking about so what's
fundamentally real is consciousness real
and this is all arising in my
consciousness is is matter fundamentally
real and my consciousness is an
epiphenomena of neural networks if we
ask a question where we were the real
answer right now is we don't fucking
know those are the best thinkers in the
world
mentally disagree on this then it's a
place where you get to actually have a
dialogue with them really on equal
footing because you actually can't even
though you can tell a whole history of
Western philosophy and Eastern
philosophy on it you that still just
brings you to I just told you a whole
lot of things about why I don't know and
so if you can come back to the like
fascination and the interest you and
you're in the same place as them and
they do have they are touching it for
the first time in different ways how do
you think we can get to to detector the
other point that I mentioned is how do
you think we can get to the point where
we're not worrying about admitting our
ignorant maybe it's not such a big deal
to a child but I think that we in in the
West loosely speaking it's it's seen as
largely not okay to admit oh I don't
know even though I feel that I should
yeah so I mean you can see what a great
tool to control other people that is yes
and you can see how little real freedom
you have and how little real ability for
peace or intimacy or honesty with other
people you have well that bullshit's
running in you now let's step back and
think about it like this for a minute
let's think about the field of the
knowable and the field of the unknowable
as ontological or ease well the thing of
them is epistemological Gauri's for a
minute they expose what the differences
yeah so ontology is in philosophy the
the inquiry into the study of what is
fundamentally real what exists and
epistemology is how do we know like you
do we think this exists because we're
measuring it in all getting the same
thing because we're experiencing it
because we're into itting it because
we're doing math like what is the what
is the right process of coming to
believe anything that we might believe
so there's this deep relationship
between what we think is real and how we
think about anything and so those are
some some of the deep categories and
philosophies so let's think about the
knowable stuff and the unknowable stuff
now Heisenberg said a limit on no
ability at the quantum mechanical level
right said the position and the momentum
of a quantum particle are not
simultaneously knowable and here's the
big deal it wasn't an epistemological
limit it wasn't we just can't get enough
information about it it was an
ontological limit they don't both exist
at the same time at the level of the
quantum it does not actually have a
fixed amount of momentum and a fixed
amount of position it has something
weirder than that like a probability
distribution about how much of those
things it has and so there is a limit to
the knowable and then you say ok well
how many quantum particles are there in
the universe and what are all the
interactions between them and how much
unknowable is there from that and it's
like ok that's you know that's a
profound set and girdle's incompleteness
theorem said set a limit on the Nobel
when it comes to mathematics right the
foundational axiomatic set of math is
infinite well we you can't no infinite
shit the nobles always finite but the
unknowable is infinite so it's important
to get first that the unknowable is a
larger class than the knowable
fundamentally and then within the
knowable you have the known and the
unknown and the known is I have a
reasonable confidence margin through
whatever process that my understanding
of this is pretty good and the unknown
is this is hypothetically knowable stuff
we just don't know it yet and there's
plenty of that within that the unknown
is also a larger class than the known is
within the knowable now why why am i
specifying this I'm specifying it
because if I think that I should know
most thing
then I actually just don't know the
deepest things about the nature of no
ability itself and so that idea like Oh
someone asked me something I don't know
there's something wrong with me like to
just realize how ridiculous that fucking
thought is yeah and its own ego and to
instead say okay well the there there is
an infinite class of things I don't know
and couldn't know and then there's a
bunch of things that I could know that I
don't and that's forever and that is
fascinating right that is in in
enthralling it's like you get to touch a
sense of awe in that and so I think that
reframe of just really getting how vast
reality is and how complex and how deep
in and then being able to have a totally
different humility in relationship to it
there's an emotional and even spiritual
element to this I think that people find
I found if you study something in depth
so when you go into the subject at first
you can make all sorts of strong and
sweeping claims because you don't know
enough to know how complicated it is and
that's quite exciting and then the more
that you learn you realize oh I feel
like I have to equivocate over
everything all the time because
everything's so complicated I wish I
could go back to when I knew less but
then the transformation can happen where
you can become comfortable knowing that
you don't know much yeah so this is a
this is a fun process right so we will
see you go to academic conference and
you'll see the top scientists in a
domain almost tripping over themselves
you do not make any real statements
because they don't want to say something
wrong in front of all the other people
that probably know a shit ton of stuff
that they that they don't know that is
relevant where what this thing might be
wrong and then you look at people who
are radically less educated about a
field and you know adamant passionate
about it so now I basically I shared
half of the story so one half is
this is actually the this is a fun story
so related to the knowable and the
unknowable and the known and the unknown
within the knowable our subjective
relationship has to do with certainty
and uncertainty and think think about it
like this
in the in the pre-modern world and most
of the kind of religious traditions and
maybe not some of the mystical
interpretations of them but at least in
in the dominant expression to the
religious traditions certainty had a
pretty high value right have certainty
that I know who the right God is and I
didn't get the wrong God and I'm
dedicated about what I'm doing the right
things not the wrong things and like and
if I get it wrong like I go to I could
go to hell instead of going to heaven or
I could reincarnate badly instead of
reincarnating well and I'm certain
enough that we can burn women as witches
and do Crusades and whatever we need to
do because we have enough certainty
about that rightness right right now
science started to emerge and have a lot
more success in in really important
things like aiming canons and you know
to practical physical things which is
actually a part of why I proliferated
and one and it acknowledged certain
kinds of uncertainties but it also gave
us the capacity for more certainty
plenty of questions like do heavy things
and light things or dense things and non
dense things fall at the same speed we
were able to start solving some of that
stuff right and earth being round or
flat or we and and so even though within
the philosophy of science the purely
uncertainty holding it as very deep a
lot of people carried the kind of
emotional orientation toward certainty
into the way they did science and wanted
to like be pretty sure that the world
started with the universe are with a big
bang and you know matter first and
biology and consciousness emerge from
neural networks and and this this isn't
actually the philosophy of science
an emotional structure of associating
certainty with security and value and
associating uncertainty with insecurity
fear and lack of value which create
which is an emotional and existential
bias leading to a cognate bias so then
post-modernism saw these flaws and it
said shit look at all the things that we
fucked up in the name of over certainty
all the things we were certain about
what we were wrong late or even within
the sciences when we were pretty certain
we had it almost all figured out around
the time of Maxwell's equations and
modern physics fucked it all up
and that's just happened so many times
we really shouldn't ever be certain
about anything because historically
we've been wrong about all of it and
whenever we were whenever we were over
certain we could do really terrible
stuff II and so then post-modernism said
we should actually embrace uncertainty
about everything and kind of all
certainty and of course I'm radically
simplifying all of pre-modern ISM and
then modernity and then post modernity
but a move towards embrace uncertainty
and any idea any narrative is just one
narrative and isn't fundamentally true
and we don't know and so then it kind of
pathologized certainty and made
uncertainty laudable and I think both of
those are untenable and you know we we
can actually see some major problems in
the world from certain interpretations
of postmodern that have led to the post
fact world that have led to increased
likelihood for strongman leaders to come
in in a post fact world but I would say
part of maturity is having a mature
relationship with certainty and
uncertainty inside of ourselves and it's
it's what you could call it epistemic
maturity which is I have a reasonable
confidence margin for certainty about
these things based on the appropriate
processes that I went through to come to
it and I have less confidence margin
about these things and I have no
confidence margin about these things
but my security and universe and my
self-worth aren't coupled to any of it
yeah yeah and that's that's a big point
that people become so emotionally
wrapped up in there and as you were
talking about that post-modernism there
I thought of someone who we featured on
the site quite a bit Jordan Peterson who
has a particular kind of gripe against
who he calls post modernists and yet the
people he's talking about seem to have
gone kind of full circle where they've
become very certain about their position
where things they're saying well there
is no inherent truth in anything and in
particular we'll talk about say cultural
relativism or cultural appropriation but
they've suddenly become dogmatic about
it which seems to totally contradict the
original point if you read Foucault
where Derrida or some of the good
postmodern philosophers there was like
real insights there right there were
they were key important insights and
they were not equally like the critiques
were not about all of the sciences
equally if you look at say the way we
did social sciences and all of the bias
that affects how we do social science
that is gonna affect the way we do
chemistry less right not none but less
and so you know there are there are
important insights there but when you
look at so let you know let's take a fun
case let's take the conversation between
Sam Harris and Dan Dennett about
freewill and consciousness these guys
are on the same team when it comes to
you know atheism and the problems of
superstitious ideas and religious
metaphysical ideas but then when it
comes to foundational ontology itself
they actually disagreed on the deepest
things one could disagree on right sam
says consciousness is real but there's
no free will
and Dan said no there is free will but
consciousness is not real like there's
our the deepest and they and they are
both philosophers of science and both
have read the same books and both
understand critical thinking it's like
well how the fuck could they come to
things that are bad
and it you know and Sam actually said
something really important in the end of
that dialogue if and if you if you've
read it but it was a fun one
he said it seems that we just have
fundamentally different intuitions and
or she is something to that effect and
that that is actually like nai there's
this thing called the symbol grounding
problem how do we get the symbols to
ground into experience right when you
when you think of an apple you know
things about the way an apple can be
tart or sweet or mealy or its skin can
kind of peel off or it can snap or like
you have so many interdependent
contextual things and you've taken it in
through a tongue and a nose and your
fingers in so many sensory organs plus
the abstraction layers of it that the
symbol has grounded right the symbol
Apple has grounded through all of those
sentry channels and so if you haven't
had some of the same sensory channels
you're not going to get the symbol
grounding in the same way so I'm
studying the chemistry of an apple but I
haven't tasted it no matter how much
fucking chemistry about an apple I've
got and I know what the EEG patterns of
people tasting it are I still don't know
what the fucking Apple tastes like and
so there is a place at which as much as
we're trying to be totally objective and
logical what what when we hear it can
land as true or not has to connect to
some experience set that lands as true
has to it is not a purely those axioms
are reasonable and can be later reified
by the process and this this was a good
process for deriving other things from
those axioms I accept it then one of the
main sources of our cognitive bias isn't
just the normal logical fallacies
everybody you know those are easy to
study it's a bunch of emotional and
existential level biases that affect the
way we process and that's where the
really subtle work comes in
few examples yeah remember the first
time that this hit me was so clearly a
very long time ago but I was I was young
I was talking to someone about there
were religious persuasion they had moved
from being a kind of New Age Hindu to a
fundamentalist Muslim and that seemed
like a very and they did that while in
mmm California upper class I'm like that
seems like a very interesting step that
doesn't make that much sense to me and
so I asked them questions about the
theology of Islam and if they really
believed these aspects of the theology
and and it wasn't getting anywhere like
it there was no place where they were
really willing to look at the aspects of
the theology I was pretty sure they
probably didn't believe and but in the
process of the way I was asking I was
actually damaging my rapport with this
person and in damaging rapport I was
damaging the ability to actually have a
meaningful conversation about this or
any topic right and so I stopped and
then I came back to let me see if I can
just create rapport about anything we
get rapport fast forward about a year
because it takes that much time to
repair the rapport from an issue like
this and I ended up finding out that
this person comes to Islam and their
particular belief someone saying this
would be true for everyone I'm saying
this one case this was a place of
realizing this person's past was that
they actually couldn't say no and they
couldn't set limits or boundaries from
themselves because of like family sexual
trauma that had happened in their
childhood and they got to a place where
they were there were some things that
happened in their life and because they
couldn't say no to some fairly terrible
things that led to their relationship
breaking whatever and they they're like
oh wow I'm gonna die basically because I
can't set limits or say no and then
right around that time they met a friend
who had just joined Islam and they were
talking about it and the rules and kind
of the absoluteness of the
rulz and that they didn't have to hold
boundaries themselves they just being
someone who believed that got to follow
those rules and at a survival level that
told this person oh she could actually
survive because she could adopt a rule
set that she now she could say no with
that reason it bought it bypassed her
childhood reasons of not being able to
say no and so what I realized was it had
nothing to do with theology even though
later the theology back felled itself as
a rationalization and so I was
addressing it it totally the wrong level
because it wasn't the level at which the
decision was made the choice wasn't made
by a deep rational introspection and
study of the theology compared to other
theologies and so then when I talked
with them about basically just childhood
and their ability to say no and set
boundaries and construct those
capacities inside of them rather than
try to deconstruct a belief once
actually felt they had that capacity
they ended up deconstructing the
religious belief on their own their
critical thinking couldn't kick in
because it was if their critical
thinking kicked in or if they allowed
anyone else's critical thinking to kick
in it would hit a survival level fear
for them of a belief that was meeting a
need and maybe it's the need to get to
still be part of your family because if
you leave the religion you won't be part
of the family or you won't be part of
the community or or you're too afraid of
death and so you know there's an extent
whatever it is or it's it's a situation
where if you say this particular thing
inside of academia and inside of the
sciences you will be shunned for saying
something that is so non-standard model
that you lose all kinds of opportunities
so there's like all these little subtle
and not-so-subtle sources of bias that
affect the process of how we go about
understanding reality it's it's also the
same sort of mechanism and thinking of
when you make a big change in your life
or maybe you leave a place of employment
and people become angry with you because
changing you're not what they expected
anymore because for them there's that
they could receive it as an implicit
implicit criticism of themselves and
their choices and that's all happening
kind of as a subtext and people are
getting angry and they maybe don't know
why they're angry yeah yeah so now you
come back to the cultural relativism and
you see okay someone might have taken
postmodern philosophy and used it as
cognitive backfill to positions that
largely came from other places they
didn't just come from a emotionally
neutral existentially neutral study of
the topics and that this was the very
best thinking they could come with him
the topic it might have been their own
trauma or witnessing a trauma in the
world that was so problematic that they
took it on or resonated with it and
that's affecting then the way they are
you know what they're resonating with
intellectually and how they're
processing it do you how do you think we
can become more aware of that in
ourselves if we if we start from the
point that we're willing to become more
aware of it a lot of these things just
sort of well up as emotions and
sometimes that's useful and sometimes
it's not but maybe if we take the
example of cultural appropriation which
is such a hot topic at the moment how do
you see that playing out for people
emotionally and how I'm and how might we
be able to have a more productive self
reflective conversation about it well
one good thing is I want to see if I can
take both sides or any side of the topic
well enough that I really get it II and
if I can't if while I'm trying to take
the other side I feel like I'm mocking
it the whole time because it just seems
so stupid then there is some bias that
won't actually allow me to see reality
through that lens and see if I'm missing
anything needs and so then part of
earnestness would be can I actually do I
know that I'm seeing what
they're seeing or am i I might not be
but I actually like notice how many
times there's a I want to stay in with
the people who share a belief similar to
me or coming to this belief that I had
answered some really critical things
that made me feel more okay or like I
had my shit together or safer in
universe or smarter and leaving that
feel scary you know you know you notice
all those kinds of things and so I would
say the degree to which we can identify
with our own earnestness to learn and
explore more than our current position
about things that's a much better
identity to the degree we need to have
one mmm I think with with the example of
cultural appropriation when I try and
think into the mind of someone who
thinks that it's pretty much always a
bad thing
it goes I've sort of two rough pictures
of what that can be driven by and one is
the more negative kind of wanting to
virtue signal and want to be right on
and sort of a cruise the sort of
certainty we talked about before that I
know that this is the this is wrong to
do it's morally wrong and therefore I'm
a good person
and the other I think comes from a place
of pain that it's hard to want to
identify with that if you feel that you
your culture or the culture of your
parents and relatives has been taken and
abused
that's quite a deep hurt and you're
coming from a place where you feel there
is no understanding of you it's a deep
alienation pain and that's also very
uncomfortable to enter into yeah so I
think this is a good process right where
you're you're not making everyone who
believes that cultural appropriation is
an issue in the same category you're
acknowledging that there might be
different epistemologies and different
processes that bring them there which is
key and then you're kind of feeling into
what those could be and some that you
can really empathize with this is not a
topic that I would say I have very deep
familiarity or expert
Easter's but but as I just think into it
right now with you there's a bunch of
things that come up right as I think
about someone who says cultural
appropriation is wrong and why that
would be I can imagine
reasons mmm deeper than just even the
pain of a culture that has been damaged
by another culture II I can imagine very
real reason so let's say we take hey
white people shouldn't wear dreadlocks
so they shouldn't wear hindu bindi so
they shouldn't you know where my Hari
Krishna chika ponytails or whatever
whatever it is right well then you say
well what were those things well there's
a superficial answer which is they were
some aesthetic whatever right but then
you go deeper well it was actually a
signaling mechanism of people who had
went through so say say in getting that
that Brahman string or getting that mall
or getting that whatever it was they had
actually went through specific ritual
specific processes practices worldview
or then they could see anyone else who
had that and they could know here's a
person that I'm gonna have a certain
amount of shared experience with and it
created a signaling that was actually
relevant not only maybe for survival
which it very much might have been in
the world where in-group out-group
dynamics are determined most of survival
but also their ability for deeper
connection trust coherence and they're
like okay that that that actually meant
something sacred
II and now if someone else is is taking
that thing without all that it meant now
I actually don't know my signaling
system is broken and I don't know if
these are people with shared experience
or not or and so you think about like
there might be layers of depth that
you're just completely missing in an
argument when you come to a position on
it and I'm not saying I think cultural
appropriation is always wrong I'm saying
I as I start to imagine in I can think
of a lot of things and I would want to
listen
a lot and I'd want to see can I be
earnest about it or does something come
up in me they starts to get blocked and
if it does I want to look at that well I
think that's that's a great attitude is
both self reflective and asking
questions but also not seeking to have a
certainty at the at the end of it and
what what comes up for me when you're
describing those sorts of single as
symbol systems and how we can read those
things is is it at the core that we have
as humans trying to understand each
other and improve ourselves are we kind
of tripping over a kind of an innate
nature which is tribal and wanting
certain systems to make sense and apply
to everybody is that something that we
can overcome they question it a dumpling
is there different questions let me
separate are we tribal and signaling
mechanisms in human nature
sure signaling mechanisms were actually
part of what helped us go beyond
tribalism because if I'm in a
hunter-gatherer society pre agrarian
society and we're below Dunbar number
right typically below 150 people maybe
meaningfully below them I actually don't
need signaling mechanisms because I know
all the people like I firsthand actually
know them all I've lived with in my
whole life and I know if it's the people
that I know and can trust or other
people that I don't know and so I
actually don't need symbolism because I
don't need an abstraction layer I'm
actually in my instantiated experience
right okay and now if we want to get a
number of tribes to be able to come
together into villages and then kingdoms
and the nation-states or you know
religious associations or whatever
larger kind of entity that has some
coherence then the question is how do we
have coherence with other people that we
don't know but that we've chosen to have
coherence for coherence with in a
situation where that was
survival relevant mmm and now signaling
mechanisms were a major part of how that
happened right so now you know your red
team or blue team the fact that you've
got a red shirt on even though I haven't
met you like I know that we're pleased
that you're playing on my side that's
called the what flag are you flying
right and so you notice with regard to
cultural appropriation like there are
people who get pretty bent out of shape
of someone who isn't a citizen of their
country using their flag in a certain
way yeah it's a it's a similar thing
right I mean so it's a related topic of
wait this is a way that our group was
able to maintain some coherence against
forces that were arrayed against it and
you know you think about like how would
US or or UK military deal with if
someone was fucking up their
intelligence system right and the
signals that were coming in to their
Intel like that would be a problem if if
you see someone like the crime of being
dressed as a police officer if you're
not a police officer or being dressed as
a military official is actually a crime
because that system of signaling is very
meaningful and and so one thing I would
say is like now many of those systems
have have interspersed so much that we
then have cultures like the u.s. that
doesn't really have a culture right it
has the mix of a whole bunch of
different things because it's fairly new
and and and so then of course it makes
sense to allow those cultures to come
together and to make new emergent things
from one perspective from another
perspective if some of those subgroups
feel like they are still needing to
maintain some of their identity for
survival or thriving reasons then it's
like wait fuck this is a real issue and
oh yeah by the way the US was built on
slavery and on the genocide and if that
hasn't even been addressed like there
there are there are issues with some of
the appropriation that are on the pain
side so I I know I went off topic a
little bit but I don't think that this
I don't think the signaling I think
that's actually an abstraction layer to
make larger cultures cohere that's not
tribalism now if by tribalism what you
really meant was in-group out-group
behavior i guess everybody did
but beyond the Dunbar number now that's
a different question are humans so
arguments capable of moving beyond the
Dumber number obviously right like being
able to have some sense of coherence
with abstracted people well that's what
what nations and religions and whatever
been and they've had they've mostly only
been able to do it through hierarchical
systems that where the there was loss of
freedom of individuals within those
systems to maintain coherence now
Machiavelli you knows enemy hypothesis
said that the only way to get a group of
people to cohere sustainably beyond the
Dunbar number is if they have a shared
outside threat that is a bigger threat
than their reason to not cohere with
each other that has been true for the
most part right like we've we you can
get you can have infighting between
Shiite and Sunni until they have the
West as a big enough you know shared foe
that they can actually unify against
that that's been true I think there's a
dynamic that's about to happen that is
different than anything that has ever
happened and I think so I think this
actually an important piece of changing
social science axioms for a minute so
how do you get the whole how do you get
everyone on this little spaceship
biosphere to recognize that they are all
inside of the same spaceship biosphere
and now we're affecting things at the
level of the whole fucking biosphere
right it's like climate change and
biodiversity loss and like all those
issues and if we have catastrophic
threats from the way we develop
exponential tech like AI or nanotech or
like these are not local issues so they
cool governance doesn't make any sense
if we're effect
each other completely like a China and
India in the US can't can't think about
climate change as countries in a
meaningful you know sentence without
what each other are doing so how do we
get that to happen well either you've
got to have some aliens attack so we can
all unify against the common enemy
you've got to abstract the enemy and say
climate change is the enemy we all need
to unify to keep ourselves from going
extinct as a species or AI is the enemy
or whatever the fuck we decide or you
can actually unify you so the first part
is you can unify against an abstract
threat right it does not have to be an
agent ik threat so something like
environmental destruction or
catastrophic risk of any kind could be a
unifying imperative it's harder but it's
possible but the next thing is we also
can unify towards shared goals where it
is more useful for us to do that than
not and this is a important thing and I
think right now we have a situation
where if we continue in group out group
dynamics there is no way to not move
into catastrophic and even existential
risk zone and so we absolutely do have
abstracted enemy hypothesis drivers of
our need to be totally cohered but we
also have you know the the kinds of
opportunities that are most interesting
to all of us are only realizable that
way why do I say this if we think about
it from a game theoretic perspective
those early tribes would cohere with
each other as a team to then if when
they needed to compete against other
tribes in a win-lose game model and they
would compete either for resource
extraction of scarce resources or direct
head-on competition through war right
through military complex and if there
was enough abundance of resources and
materials that it was easier to take
shit from nature from the Commons and
fight each other then they wouldn't
fight if the there started to be
scarcity and fighting each other be
directly or indirectly became a
necessity or an easier thing to do then
that happened and then of course if
there's a
larger tribe and we can't actually fight
them competently then we might unify
with some other smaller tribes but then
now we're bigger that's gonna have them
do it now we're at villages and then
they're gonna keep unifying and creating
better now we need signalling systems
right now we need culture larger and so
will eventually get nation-states and
economic trading blocks but as as we
think about this kind of what we've
called civilization growing from tribes
into what we what we have now of you
know kinds of large conglomerated
superpower dynamics where the ability we
were our ability to compete with each
other for extracting scarce resource
from the earth is actually getting us
towards the points of making the earth
not habitable across major regions and
where then you start getting you know
massive refugee human migration issues
that start to collapse Grid
infrastructure that can't handle it over
the next little bit Syria was already an
example of that droughts leading to
people moving from subsistence farming
areas into the city leading to resource
shortage leading to the war and the
escalation that happened and it was
basically a small one but also even then
you know these groups in war with each
other we don't we can't use our weapons
right like are they china and russia in
the u.s. like we just can't get into a
war with each other so we will try and
deal with them as proxy wars or whatever
but we have weapons that are powerful
enough that winning would again ste
other one since the other one also has
powerful enough shit winning would
require destroying the whole playing
field for everybody when you get to
enough power in a game theoretic
situation where winning requires
destroying the playing field so it
equals losing even for the winner and
win lose game theory becomes omni lose
lose because there's that much power
then you either have to get off game
theory entirely and this means in-group
out-group dynamics or you go or you go
extinct or very near right you have a
massive step
in in capacity catastrophic or
accidental risk I think in the next very
little bit very short number of years we
either continue competing for the
extraction of scarce resources moving
the biosphere towards more you know
critical fragility and keep competing
with each other in heads on fashions
that end up and competing for more
powerful tech that leads to exponential
tech that is autocatalytic and can run
away from us in a number of different
ways and we we we will have then a
radical step down in civilization either
no civilization or a radical step down
if we continue doing that or we actually
figure out what the fuck Omni win-win on
a little-bitty biosphere where we're all
in it together means and it means it it
means something where nations are an
obsolete idea they might have served
evolutionary relevance but they don't
anymore and it means something where
private balance sheets that where you
want to accumulate more shit on your
balance sheet because it leads to new
capacities but scarce stuff that other
people don't have and where nature
doesn't have a balance sheet so all of
the economic incentive is to externalize
cost to nature take shit out of nature
and compete with each other for that
shit served evolutionary relevance but
can't go further either so there is some
you know the a post win-lose game theory
a post in-group out-group mentality
requires a complete shift to economics
completion to governance complete shift
to culture religion all the way down to
a shifted identity where I'm not even a
fucking separate being in my mind of
course I'm an individual and actually
even a totally unique non fungible
individual but I'm an individual that
wouldn't exist without the whole rest of
it they wouldn't exist without an
atmosphere with oxygen that wouldn't
exist in the way that I am without other
people doing a gazillion functions that
my life depends on and when I get that
we're all these emergent properties of
an interconnected whole and unique amar
properties that are not replaceable at
that identity level we can start getting
something that can transcend in-group
out-group dynamics this reminds me of I
don't know if you've read a book called
finite and infinite games yep James
course yeah it's a great read for those
who haven't read it there's he outlines
a perspective on essentially everything
in human life where we can see it as a
game and a finite game there's winners
and losers and a clear outcome and it's
it's finite it's not going to be
something you could repeat it you could
do multiple times in the series but each
outcome is kind of set whereas the point
of an infinite game is to keep playing
so like a relationship or we would say
the human species if this is the game
we're playing what we want to do is not
to have winners and losers but to be
able to enable the game to continue
rolling along and yeah it's it's a great
foundational book and I highly recommend
it for everyone and it has so many
layers of depth and meaning built in
that if you're if you're reading it it's
a treatise on economics and governance
and spirituality and human psychology at
the same time but that core idea that
finite games are meant to be won and
when you win the game's over and
infinite games are meant to continue the
game of play it's a it is a so we're
looking at a shift from win-lose game
theory to Omni win-win or a different
concept even of what win means from
mostly zero-sum to increasingly positive
some from finite to infinite there's a
whole shift but that new thing isn't
even anything like what we have called a
game previously yeah and if and if to
win is to play then this brings us to a
couple of points of ideas that people
have talked about I know you talked
about the Commons as a key reference
point in your work where things that are
common like the common resources or the
the things that are common to everyone
like the environment but then we face
the problem of say hardly anybody who
uses Wikipedia actually contributes to
it
and how can we change that perspective
and then there's another obvious example
which is the idea of a universal basic
income which would enable people to keep
playing their lives without feeling that
if they they don't do certain things
they're simply not going to be able to
play at all and I wonder if you could
comment on the usual objections that
come up against those which tend to be
people are selfish and they don't care
about others how can we reconfigure AI
people's ideas of what the game is that
they're playing yeah so you're asking
questions that to really deconstruct a
lot of our ideas around evolutionary
biology and evolutionary psychology and
what we think of as human nature
genetically and economic theory and then
adequately reconstruct new things would
take enough time that I'm not gonna get
to do it I'm gonna just push push
buttons of all of those I think that we
have got human conditioning that is
actually relatively new but that has
become very ubiquitous because it was
successful in a win-lose game theoretic
structure and it's so skubick with us
that we've done pretty much all of our
social science within that context and
so we stopped factoring the context and
call it human nature we we've done
almost all of our social sciences within
capitalism we've done almost all of it
within nation-states right within those
kinds of structures done it within win
lose game theory in a mostly
post-industrial definitely post agrarian
world most the history of our species
was pre agrarian definitely pre nation
say and you know pre agrarian also meant
pre capital pre private ownership of
surplus because there was no fucking
surplus and so there's a totally
different relationship to those things
so uh and then we say okay well the way
that we're behaving since it's
ubiquitous must be nature rather than
nurture so then let's try and look for
the genes that correlate and make it a
genetic answer and this is where I think
our our biases lead to bad science
so I won't go further down there but I
will say that most of what we call in a
Leah Boleyn is our nature expressed
through a certain set of conditions and
different enough conditions can can have
what is nature expressed differently now
I'm gonna come back and say the whole
nature-nurture what is fundamentally
possible to the human condition
it we can ask a thought experiment about
it that's different than we've been able
to ask previously because CRISPR is
making the conversation of human genetic
engineering a real not that far off
possible conversation right it's a big
fucking deal because if we say ok well
maybe maybe there is something that is
genetic and maybe we can change those
genes then it brings up D instantly now
we're in deep existentialism around oh
if we can actually change something that
we thought of as nature what is
fundamentally desirable outside of what
we thought was a fixed context right
should do we want to then change the
genes where everyone is a hyper
competitor do we and and they're the
most violent and largest alpha men
possible only do we want to make it
toward now alphas are irrelevant and
everyone is a super cooperator do we
want to make it to where people are
happy all the time and we have done the
abolitionist imperative and got rid of
the ability to suffer and feel pain or
do we like are there evolutionary and
psychological purposes that stay
relevant to like now we're in a very
deep existential philosophic and it's
important that we go there now as soon
as we can start to you know ask those
questions then we can come back to ok
well here are some things that are
meaningful about the human condition
what of them might actually be possible
even without the genetic engineering but
it does make us start thinking that the
what we have thought of as human nature
that was a hard unfixed limit we can at
least think about it more flexibly which
i think is a useful thought experiment
but
if you have us if you have a situation
where there's a lot of shitty jobs right
like tarring roads is just not that fun
and you know etc etc so it doesn't mean
that nobody would would never want to go
do some touring of a road or different
kinds of labor or different kinds of
rote tasks but most people wouldn't want
to do 50 hours of it a week for 40 years
right yeah and yet the society has
needed people to do a bunch of that shit
and so when you then see people as the
vector for getting societal things done
you have to have an extrinsic motives
system to get people to do it so if we
all pull our resources and then make
sure everybody has resources we call it
communism then then why would anyone do
the shitty jobs well now the state has
to force them so we call it imperialism
and that's why we don't like communism
I'm radically oversimplifying of course
but that's like at the heart of the
argument so then we say cool let's let
the free market force people because
that's better so we're the states not
going to force people but if but they
don't get any basic needs met so if they
don't go do one of the shitty jobs they
starve now we'll say that they have the
freedom to get better education and
hopefully not have to do the shitty jobs
but of course it's not a real argument
since a lot of people are gonna have to
do the shitty jobs because somebody has
to right and those who are born into
families where someone else was doing it
have a lot less likelihood to have
access to good education and good health
care and good training and so in a
situation where the default is having
nothing you need to get stuff to just
survive bottom of Maslow's hierarchy but
now surviving doesn't give me the next
levels of Maslow's hierarchy right like
my belonging the more shit that I get
the more I'll be able to actually get
relationships and do things with friends
that have the resources to do stuff and
and my esteem all the way up to my
self-actualization the more that I can
get shit the more capacity I have to
self express and do and like that every
level of Mao's Lahiri if I want it and
we value the scare shit where you having
something then you don't have access to
it like a
shopping cart you have possession of it
where when you're not using it I still
can't use it and so because you
possessing some scarce thing there's not
enough of for everybody means that I
don't have access we're we're in
fundamental competition with each other
right and if there's something that's
abundant enough that you having it
doesn't decrease my access at all like
air we put no economic value at all on
it because there's no ability to have
differential advantage associated with
getting some of the scarce thing and
because we put no economic value on the
air will pollute the shit out of it and
burn it up because it doesn't enter our
economics calculus is the basis of our
decision-making but we'll work really
hard to get the gold or the diamond or
whatever it is that we perceive as
scarce nuff said if I have it gives me
some differential advantage over you but
then I'm gonna take that gold of them in
and put it in a safe that is doing
nothing for anyone other than a Fiat
purpose right and then because it scarce
know this is important to get because
the value is proportional to the
scarcity because we're not looking for
systemic advantage we're looking for
differential competitive advantage which
just assumed if the thing became
unscared so it would have no value like
air so as soon as we start finding that
diamonds aren't as scarce as we thought
they were we start burning and crushing
and hiding them right you know we need
to artificially manufacture scarcity so
when you have a system where if you
don't get shit you die and if you don't
get more shit you don't get to express
very well and anyone else getting shit
means you don't have it and win-lose
dynamics everywhere like if you if I
wanted to condition greed and
selfishness and jealousy and the people
the best I could
that's how the fuck I would do it is
that you trading that exactly and if I
wanted to train people to be Psychopaths
right not like I put them through enough
first person childhood trauma or they
have the right kind of brain injuries or
genes for formal psychopathy but I want
to decrease their empathy pretty
radically and their ability to
rationalize harm well I would do things
like capitalism and large you know and
then the evolutions of capitalism that
happen corporate capitalism where
if you aren't willing to participate in
something that's gonna have
externalities you just don't get to run
a big company if you're running a big
company you've got to say yeah shit well
those mines are run by slave labor but
like there's just no other mines and if
we tried to pay for fair trade we'd be
totally out of business so you got it
like crack some eggs to make some
omelets just even being able to
participate with a system that isn't
closed-loop that doesn't actually value
all the metrics that it effects requires
rationalizing harm and having a kind of
abstracted psychopathy so you know we
have a system that you can think of as
conditioning low-grade whoo Bick wit a
psychopathy and everybody and then we do
social science on it we call it human
nature yeah and then we can't change it
then we'd use that to rationalize the
system again continuing it exactly but
like you know if I walk by a homeless
person and they have they're in real
pain right they might even be bleeding
they might be really dirty they and I
just walk by because I'm busy I got shit
to do and maybe I give him five bucks
but I you know I walk by there is
something wrong with me at a human level
there is some way that I was able to
turn my empathy off where this
disappointment I got to get to that is
trivial as fuck in comparison to this
other person's whole life I just I can
and I can be fine just continuing to be
worried about my busyness like what the
fuck how could I do that
well because there's so many homeless
people I can't fix all of them and then
that then that rationalizes none of them
right but that's that systemic that is a
system where empathy isn't even viable
in the system and so everybody has to
turn it down or go crazy yeah it's also
like a personal if I don't know if the
language makes sense but it's a
personally systemic thing that if you
think you can't help all the people then
you won't help one
then you never helped anybody yeah and
so well you know cuz it doesn't you say
alright I can try and do this like I'll
help this one thing but then if I'm if I
care about this one enough to really
help them I turn my feeling back on
rights then you on the day my feeling
back on now what about the next one and
the next one and when do I stop but also
and when do I decide that actually
upgrading from my last year's Mercedes
to this next year's Mercedes is worth
more than helping a couple more of them
how are you gonna say my time well in
this system when you do help that other
person you might depends on the extent
you help them but you also start risking
your own safety and future so if you if
you you really want to help them you
want to give them all the resources and
you already have you yourself living
scarcity which a lot of people do like
you have to take care of your own shit
first before you can help anyone else
well that's the story right that's the
that's the story that we tell and then
of course now this is a very painful
thing to say but most people then if you
look at at the end of their life the
amount of shit that they've consumed and
what that did to the environment what it
did to however many animals that were
involved how many species went extinct
related to those supply chains how many
animals in factory farms and then how
many migrant workers how many people in
sweat shops etc and you and you look at
all of that and then you compare it to
what that person then did once they got
ahead well enough to help other people
like there they are on the liability
side of nature's balance sheet yes now
the answer is not obvious because the
answer doesn't exist within this system
the answer is actually needing to build
new systems that don't take complexity
and make it simple or complicated right
that don't do win-lose game-theoretic
structures so when when you look at this
it is it's actually there aren't obvious
answers the
good and meaningful about how to like
okay how do we prevent war and have a
world full of peace like why the fuck do
we still have war it would seem like
world peace is something everybody wants
okay well how do you have a for-profit
military-industrial complex as the
largest block of global economics and
understanding the laws of supply and
demand have a world that doesn't have
war like how do those two things get to
live together they don't they don't
right and so then when we say well we're
working on peace are you working to
obsolete having a for-profit
military-industrial complex cuz if not
you have no chance of addressing it
because any system of supply has to
continue to maintain and protect and
grow its source of demand and that's
even just the directors following their
fiduciary responsibility to the
shareholders of the company I mean like
that so the point is it's a the system
as a whole
it's a paperclip Maximizer and there's
there's an identity problem here at the
core to you that if you're trying to say
obsolete a military-industrial complex
the people within it don't want to be
obsoleted but in the same way that
somebody who has spent their whole life
tearing the roads and that's the only
skill they feel they have they also
don't want to be obsoleted because
there's that sense of existential
confusion and angst over well well what
am i then I'm being forced to become
something else and that's frightening
right right so the shift that has to
happen does include a macro structural
shift but it also includes individual
both trauma and attachments level shifts
and identity level shifts right because
most people's identity like that not
most people everybody's identity was
conditioned by a system and it's
adaptive within it and it's actually
maladaptive to making something else and
then I guess we come back to the
question of still wanting to have
control over your life and how things
make sense but if we're talking about a
radical shift in human development
something that we've come to think of as
human nature which you said likely it's
just something we call human nature
because it's been the case for long
enough that we think it's fundamental
the we have to overhaul some very basic
structures of thoughts here so looking
looking forward at that process do you
think this is we're a chrysalis about to
turn into a butterfly or are you kind of
more worried than that I think that if
we just okay first I will say that we
have what I might call kind of naive
Tecna is Amaya there much of Silicon
Valley is famous for right and that that
narrative is also connected to kind of
this that dialectic of progress that we
used to have these short brutish nasty
lives and should have just been getting
continuously better with capitalism and
tech and industry you know on a on a
consistent path and it's gonna continue
forever and every problem we have that
ahead we don't really have to worry
about because human ingenuity always
figures it out
I do think that this is radically naive
i I think that is a more dangerous world
view than fundamentalist religious
worldviews interest because the
fundamentalist religious worldviews
can't create new tech that gives us more
power and having more power
exponentially more power to affect shit
without having comprehensively better
decision making means exponential
externality equals catastrophic risk we
have a scenario right now where
exponential tech is means we are
exponent we don't know how to make an
intuition around exponents because we've
never had them right we we've got we can
maybe make a sense out of like curves
that are slightly inflected up for a
short period of time but not really
right so with an exponential curve our
intuition can't really make
but we have exponentially increasing
capacity to affect the world around us
militarily and through supply chains and
through extraction technology and there
are positive applications because
thermodynamics just works that way right
like there there's one way to put all
the pieces of a cell together where it's
a cell and it respirate s' there's lots
of fucking ways to take it apart and so
and it takes a year to build a house or
six months but it takes a few minutes
with a record ball to break it down
entropy is just easier so when we
develop new technological capacity that
negative applications have higher
probabilities if I'm just looking at an
even playing field of probability so we
have to factor that so if we're two
things we're exponentially increasing
our capacity to affect the world around
us while simultaneously decreasing the
quality of our decision-making in many
areas because exponential increase in
information technology combined with an
economic structure we're having
information having data is competitive
advantage in a system where I need
competitive advantage so I want to both
hide things that are true and I want to
even share disinformation right like
fake left and then go right to make get
the competitor off of that we have all
sorts of incentive to diss dissing form
but with exponential information Technic
then we get such a glut of noise that
you can't even identify signal clearly
and so this is why we're in this kind of
post fact world where it's like okay how
long do we have with climate change
before the coral died nobody fucking
knows how much uranium is Fukushima
really releasing or how close is it to a
to a reactor meltdown or or can North
Korea's nuke SRIA Lee hit North America
or not or or did Russia really meddle in
the election or like we actually don't
have the ability to make sense of
fucking anything
that matters to whether we survive as a
species or not because the dissin firm
so we've had this escalating
disinformation for reasons that make
sense right for just competitive
advantage on information and reach an
incentive to do dis inform him but that
means decrease capacity to make sense of
the world which means decrease capacity
to make good choices with increased
capacity to make powerful choices so
techno up Tamizh I'm why I say it's a
dangerous world view is because it is
actually capable of advancing the tech
that within the current structure is
self terminating and so we do need to
say ok shit nature does this complex
self-organizing so adaptive resilient
thing the era of evolutions defined by
it how do we make a complex human built
world that is that has closed loops that
doesn't have externality that is
continuously adaptive rather than a
complicated one and how do we do it in
harmony with a complex system of nature
rather than you know with nature as a
finite consumable substrate we have to
figure that out and that that is of
course even more advanced tech and more
advanced science but fundamentally
different oh so you were asking I'm
sorry the question does are we gonna
make it are we not gonna make it how
does it look well if I just plot the
current curves the current curves don't
look good ii-if if we look at any of the
groups working on global catastrophic
risk assessment next essential risk
assessment the probability is of really
problematic stuff our way to highway 2
near term now that said you know you
asked this question about caterpillar
into a butterfly this is a really
interesting question because if I didn't
know the caterpillar was going to go
into a chrysalis and do the butterfly
and I was just watching the caterpillar
grow and I was forecasting a curve I
would assume that it just kept becoming
a bigger and bigger caterpillar and
eating more and more shit until it
decimated all the plants and ate itself
to extinction
yeah and so I can't keep plotting that
curve because it's not gonna do that
curve it's gonna do that curve to a
certain point where it's actually eaten
enough stuff meaning the caterpillar is
a net consumption machine right like it
doesn't pollinate stuff all it does is
devastate everything around it consuming
but it's getting the raw materials the
minerals amino acids to make a butterfly
so but as this consumption machine it is
devastating the environment around it
but once it eats enough stuff that it
has the fuel and resources necessary to
make a butterfly the imaginal cells the
first butterfly cells start kicking on
triggers the movement into the chrysalis
at which point the caterpillar ends up
dissolving like all the organs is
alright dissolves all the way down to
sub cellular structures and then gets to
reform right at an amino acid at a
peptide level reform to a butterfly that
is not a retrofit of a caterpillar it's
it's a fundamentally different thing of
the fundamentally different code but you
wouldn't have predicted that discrete
phase shift by just continuing to
forecast along the caterpillar curve
anymore than you would if you just took
the 40 weeks of in utero development and
said it looks bad right like if we
didn't know birth was gonna happen
it's getting really cramped around 42
weeks around 44 weeks it looks like it's
just gonna like get too big and die
right and this the same can be true said
true for a little bird developing inside
of an eggshell right like they're all
the developmental phases are defined by
net consumption and net growth in a
finite self terminating way to get to
the point that of course if it tried to
continue it would go it would die but
it's to get to the point that it has the
capacity to go through some discrete
phase shift the chrysalis the birth out
of the uterus and the cutting of the
umbilical cord the emergence out of the
eggshell and then on the other side of
that discrete
a ship is a totally new curve and so
then the question is could there be a
discrete phase shift that where all of
what we've called humanity or
civilization so far has been a
developmental phase where we were
focused on with capitalism military
industrial complex all the civilization
structures we're focused on gathering
the parts necessary to build a truly
global sustainable regenerative anti
fragile complex civilization but now
it's not going to be an extension of the
current system it is a dissolve and then
restructure those technologies those
capacities for a fundamentally new
reason for being and that is I would say
the the hope and the possibility is a
world where win lose game theory got us
a lot of capacity to actually not just
be a tribal people but a global people
but now we actually have to transcend at
the place where we've gotten so much
power to win that that power actually
can't be used without destroying itself
we have to now transcend win lose game
theory right I guess so
I'd say last question for this this part
of discussion then are you optimistic
about that do you think this is going to
be the chrysalis moment and that we're
going to just be creating or turn into a
new paradigm of some kind
is there enough cause for hope that we
could feel that way it's a tricky
question there there's a utilitarian
answer which is depending upon what is
going to move people more it's important
for them to hold both sides right if if
getting that it's not a given that we
make it can shake someone enough from
just wanting to win at a dying game then
they might need to go through that and I
think probably most people do and it's
important but then not stay stuck there
and then say okay well now I don't want
to win at a dying
or a game that is causing the death of
what is meaningful itself I want to help
birth a new game now what is what is
that it's if you think of it as
inevitable then it doesn't necessarily
compel your participation if you think
of it as impossible it doesn't compel
your participation either if you think
of it as possible and not yet determined
and influenceable by how you show up I
think that's the right way to think
about it so I have one last question in
this regard what can we do then on an
individual level to make this shift
happen yeah so I'm gonna answer that in
a meta way first ask that question
earnestly a lot and really work for
answers without assuming that any
authority already has them and not
assuming that there aren't places that
have a lot of answer that you want to
study right but like for whatever faults
we can assess there Gandhi did some very
meaningful things that have have not
been done at that scale maybe maybe ever
and one of the interesting parts of the
story when he said you know in South
Africa the first time then in India
later he said okay I'm gonna I'm gonna
stop this I'm gonna get a home rule for
India and people said how he said I have
no idea mm-hmm
but he said like I know that it's right
I know that these people being enslaved
by another people is not right I know
that's right so I'm commended to
aligning my life to make it happen fully
before knowing how there's a decision
before the problem solving and so then
it was like then because of that and he
said so my how I'm gonna just sit here
in Journal and think about it and
meditate and pray and do whatever
process I have to come up with the how
and then when I give that how I'm gonna
try it and then when it failed he was
like no I didn't they always learn
something kind of like Edison's aibum
tre again we have to take something
an approach where there is a where
there's a knowing that we don't actually
know how to do this fundamentally new
phase yet we want to learn from all the
people that have been thinking well
about it and we want to be thinking well
about it and we want to be adding our
energy to it as best as we can and we
want to get really fucking earnest about
that and notice wait where am I actually
just kind of mostly trying to win at the
current system and and what does that
mean and think more deeply about it so
the first thing I would say is is really
that like rather than yeah rather than
you know me give an answer do this thing
it's activate yourself as an agent of
sense making as a capable being that can
actually make sense of shit and think
about it and and work on something and
so the the answer what can you do I one
thing that it is not is donate some
money to charity and go do some
volunteer work sometimes and recycle and
like ride your bike to work all of that
is lovely and we we still hit
catastrophe if that's the if that's the
best we're doing because it's not like
decrease our personal consumption a
little bit try and do some good stuff
changes anything at scale Oh like people
have to take a deeper level of
responsibility for how do we actually
change these meta systems what could a
future of economics post capitalism
that's viable really look like so then
you say well I don't know let's start
studying at steady post capitalism and
and study different systems that have
been proposed and then look out what are
groups that are working on things and is
there something I can meaningfully
contribute all right well that system
makes sense but I have no idea how the
fuck we get there
all right what might a transitional
system its intelligible to the current
system but vectors towards that so maybe
aspects of The Venus Project and
resource-based economy's are not fully
dialed in but there are parts of it that
are right but how do you vector there
may be some parts of crypto currency
blockchain is also inadequate but maybe
convector that you start kind of really
dialing in what are the closest things
we know for how to
think about both what a viable
civilization could look like and how we
can vector there and yeah I mean that
that's what I would really say is think
about it earnestly educate yourself and
work on it and actually realize that it
matters that's really helpful thank you
yeah I agree
that's definitely it's keeping an it's
an active mind and not just looking for
quick fixes which I guess is part of the
core of what what your work is and what
neuro hacker is trying to do if people
want to find out more about your own
thinking and writing as well as neuro
hacker where can they go to find you you
know all of this work on kind of
macroeconomics and sense-making in
governance and infrastructure there is
no place that that's hosted on the web
yet but there is about to be we you know
we have some kind of think tank like
organizations that focus on these things
but it they're not publishing at some
point they might I'll let you know I'm
about to put up a website in like a week
or so and I'll give you the URL it'll be
civilization emerging calm or something
like that but you know for right now
there's people can come make friends on
Facebook and maybe see some things and
neural hackers not really focused on you
know future of macroeconomics whatever
directly but it is focused on can we
develop can we you know take complex
system science and develop better
technologies to help humans have the
capacity to participate in these things
more meaningfully so if you're
interested in that topic then nor hacker
has interesting resources
yeah that's neuro hacker comm for people
to check that out and looking forward to
in a future conversation talking deeply
about optimizing and improving our human
capacity so then from which point
hopefully we can tackle some of these
bigger issues we've been talking about
and I guess learn how to play a
different game in the process
so yeah thanks so much for your time and
for sharing all of this Daniel I've I've
learned a lot and I've really enjoyed
the conversation likewise these were
these were fun questions and topics and
I appreciate it and you know on the
topic of what can we do to help
meaningfully transform civilization
looking at the model did that y'all are
working on which is you know what I said
is people should work to educate
themselves meaningfully and study and
explore both outside Education and
mining their own thinking where are the
sources of good information that are
relevant and I see that that's what you
all have been working to do here is
bring together resources so that's I'm
very happy about thank you thank you so
much you can't compliment thanks for
listening if you appreciate the high
existence podcast the best way to
support it is to invest in yourself by
acquiring one or more of our self
development tools at story existence
calm use the code wisdom and check out
to get a huge twenty five percent off
the thirty challenges to enlightenment
course you can also leave reviews on
iTunes or share it with your friends on
social media thank you so much for
tuning in and cheers to a high existence
[Music]
[Applause]